Bengisu Caqiltay

PHD CANDIDATE · COMPUTER SCIENCES

University of Wisconsin-Madison, 1210 W Dayton St, Madison, WI 53706

Research Interests _

I take a family-centered approach to develop design requirements for social companion robots tailored to the needs and preferences of children and families. Through qualitative and design-based research, I study user interactions and explore how these technologies can be used to improve families' lives, facilitate routines, and support connections. I take an interdisciplinary lens, in the intersection of computer science, cognitive science, social robotics, design, and family studies.

Education ___

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Madison, Wisconsin Fall 2020 - present

PHD COMPUTER SCIENCES, MINOR: HUMAN DEVELOPMENT AND FAMILY STUDIES

• Advisor: Dr. Bilge Mutlu

Middle East Technical University

Ankara, Turkey

2018 - 2020

MS COGNITIVE SCIENCE

• Advisor: Dr. Cengiz Acarturk

• "An investigation of interactions with conversational violations: Insights from visual perception and Gricean Maxim violations"

Bilkent University Ankara, Turkey **BS COMPUTER SCIENCE** 2014 - 2018

Publications —

- Cagiltay, B., Mutlu, B., (2024). "Toward Family-Robot Interactions: A Family-Centered Framework in HRI" In Proceedings of the 2023 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI 24).
- Cagiltay, B., Mutlu, B., & Kerr, M. (2023). Family Theories in Child-Robot Interactions: Understanding Families as a Whole for Child-Robot Interaction Design. In Interaction Design and Children (IDC 23) ACM.
- Cagiltay, B., Mutlu, B., & Michaelis, J. E. (2023). "My Unconditional Homework Buddy:" Exploring Children's Preferences for a Homework Companion Robot. In Interaction Design and Children (IDC 23) ACM.
- Cagiltay, B. (2023, April). Designing for In-Home Long-Term Family-Robot Interactions: Family Preferences, Connection-Making, and Privacy. In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems ACM.
- Praveena, P.*, Cagiltay, B.*, Gleicher, M., & Mutlu, B. (2023, April). Exploring the Use of Collaborative Robots in Cinematography. In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems ACM.
- Cagiltay, B.*, Michaelis, J. E.*, Ibtasar, R., & Mutlu, B. (2023, March). "Off Script:" Design Opportunities Emerging from Long-Term Social Robot Interactions In-the-Wild. In Proceedings of the 2023 ACM/IEEE International Conference on HRI.
- Lee, C., Cagiltay, B., Sullivan, D., & Mutlu, B. (2023, March). Demonstrating the Potential of Interactive Product Packaging for Enriching Human-Robot Interaction. In Companion of the 2023 ACM/IEEE International Conference on HRI
- Cagiltay, B., Michaelis, J., Sebo, S., and Mutlu, B. 2022. Exploring Children's Preferences for Taking Care of a Social Robot. In Interaction Design and Children (IDC 22). ACM. Best Short Paper Award
- Cagiltay, B., White, N., Ibtasar, R., Mutlu, B., & Michaelis, J. (2022, July) Understanding Factors that Shape Children's Long Term Engagement with an In-Home Learning Companion Robot. In Interaction Design and Children (IDC 22)ACM.
- Lee, C.+, Cagiltay, B., & Mutlu, B. (2022, May) The Unboxing Experience: Exploration and Design of Initial Interactions Between Children and Social Robots. In CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI'22). Article 151, 1-14. **ACM. Best Paper Honorable Mention Award**

^{*} equal contribution; + mentored graduate student

- Tang, B., Chandrasekaran, V., **Cagiltay, B.**, Sullivan, D., Fawaz, K., Mutlu, B. (HRI 2022) Confidant: A Privacy Controller for Social Robots. In *Proceedings of the 2022 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction (HRI'22)*. IEEE
- Suero Montero, C., **Cagiltay, B.**, Dindar, K., Kärnä, E., Kilpiä, A., Pihlainen, K., Kämäräinen, A. (2022) Analysing Inclusive Groups' Peer Interactions Using Mobile Eye Tracking in Educational Context, In *EDULEARN22 Proceedings*
- Suero Montero, C., Kilpia, A., Kamarainen, A., **Cagiltay, B.**, Karna, E., Cagiltay, K., Pihlainen, K., & Karasu, N. (2022). Mobile Eye Tracking Research in Inclusive Classrooms: Children's Experiences. *In 2022 International Conference on Advanced Learning Technologies (ICALT)* IEEE
- Cagiltay, B.*, White, N. T.*, Michaelis, J. E., & Mutlu, B. (2021, June). Designing Emotionally Expressive Social Commentary to Facilitate Child-Robot Interaction. In *Interaction Design and Children* (pp. 314-325). ACM.
- Ho, H. R., **Cagiltay, B.**, White, N. T., Hubbard, E. M., & Mutlu, B. (2021, June). RoboMath: Designing a Learning Companion Robot to Support Children's Numerical Skills. In *Interaction Design and Children*. (pp. 283-293). ACM.
- Zhao, F., White, N., **Cagiltay, B.**, Niedenthal, P., Michaelis, J. E., & Mutlu, B. (2021). Designing Emotional Expressions for a Reading Companion Robot. In *Society for Affective Science Conference (SAS 2021)*.
- **Cagiltay, B.,** Ho, H. R., Michaelis, J. E., & Mutlu, B. (2020, June). Investigating family perceptions and design preferences for an in-home robot. In *Proceedings of the interaction design and children conference* (pp. 229-242). ACM.
- **Cagiltay, B.** (2020). An investigation of interactions with conversational violations: Insights from visual perception and Gricean Maxim violations (*Master's thesis, Middle East Technical University*)

Research Experience _

Graduate Research Assistant - People and Robots Laboratory

Madison, WI

ADVISOR: DR. BILGE MUTLU

Jun. 2019 - Ongoing

• Designing Learning Companion Robots for Children
Conducting qualitative and quantitative research in human-robot interaction and designing educational robots for children.
Laboratory Website: peopleandrobots.wisc.edu

Meta (Formerly Facebook) - Privacy Org

Menlo Park. CA

QUALITATIVE UX RESEARCHER INTERN

May. 2022 - Sep. 2022

· Project: Privacy Education for Teens, Privacy Regulatory Readiness, UX Research Team

University of Eastern Finland - Dept. of Special Education

Joensuu, Finland

ADVISOR: DR. EIJA KARNA

Sep. 2019 - Sep. 2022

PEICAS - Peer Interactions involving Children with Autism Spectrum disorder in inclusive classrooms
 Collaborated on an interdisciplinary eye-tracking study to understand social participation patterns of children with autism.
 Project Website: peicas.fi

Middle East Technical University - Dept. of Cognitive Science

Ankara, Turkey

ADVISOR: DR. CENGIZ ACARTURK

Feb. 2018 - Nov. 2020

Visual Cognition Research using Eye-Tracking Technologies
 Conducted research in visual cognition and human-computer interaction using eye-tracking technologies.

 Proficiency in Tobii and SMI eye-tracking devices and software.

Nielsen Data Analytics Istanbul, Turkey

• Neuro-Marketing Research

FREELANCE RESEARCHER

Collected and analyzed data for a multi-modal neuro-marketing study using eye tracking and fNIRS.

University of Alabama - Dept. of Educational Neuroscience and Computer Sciences

Tuscaloosa, AL

2019

ADVISORS: DR. FIRAT SOYLU AND DR. JEFF GRAY

Jul. 2017 - Sep. 2017

Embodied Learning Design and Educational Neuroscience Lab
 Supported angoing research in numerical cognition, number gestures, and the supported angoing research in numerical cognition.

Advisor: Dr. Fırat Soylu

Supported ongoing research in numerical cognition, number gestures, and finger counting in mathematical development, using neuroimaging techniques, i.e. EEG. *Laboratory Website*: elden.ua.edu

Computer Science Department

Advisor: Dr. Jeff Gray

Mentored in a summer programming class for high-school students.

Mentoring Experience 2021–2022 Christine Lee, PhD Student, Computer Sciences, UW-Madison 2021–2023 Batuhan Bayraktar, Bachelors Honors Thesis, Computer Sciences, UW-Madison 2022 Jingyu Chen, Lisette Lurker, NSF REU, Computer Sciences, UW-Madison Awards and Recognition 2023 CHI 2023 Doctoral Consortium Award, CHI Conference of Human Factors in Computing \$ 1,800 Special Recognition for Outstanding Reviews, Four (4) in ACM CHI, One (1) in ACM DIS

Invited Talks_

Jan 11, 2024. Robots and Routines: Exploring the Future of Social Robots in Family Life. Invited talk: Talking Robotics Webinar. youtu.be/m0yFQOXCDMY

Nov 17, 2023. Robots and Routines: Exploring the Future of Social Robots in Family Life. Invited talk: CS Colloquium - Rising Stars in HCI, Iowa City, Iowa. cs.uiowa.edu/event/130806/0

Professional Development _

Workshop, Chair, CHI 2024, "Methods for Family-Centered Design" Website: bit.ly/fcd-chi2024

Workshop, Chair, IDC 2023, "From Child-Centered to Family-Centered Interaction Design" Website: bit.ly/idc23fcid

Special Research Topic, *Coordinator*, Frontiers in Robotics & Al 2023, Title: "From Child-Centered to Family-Centered Design for New Technology"

Doctoral Consortium, Attendee, CHI 2023, Acceptance rate 20/115 submissions.

Morgridge Entrepreneurial Bootcamp, Attendee, June 2023, University of Wisconsin-Madison

Workshop, Demonstrator, Cognitive Developmental Society 2022. "A Reading Companion Robot for Children"

SERVICE AND OUTREACH

2023, Oct	First Annual Midwest HRI Meetup, Student Co-Organizer, University of Wisconsin-Madison,	Chicago, IL
	University of Chicago (Host), University of Illinois at Chicago	- <i>J</i> - <i>y</i>
2023, Oct	ACM CSCW 2023, Student Volunteer	Minneapolis
2023, May	People and Robots Lab, Hiring Manager, Editor and Illustrator Positions	Madison, WI
2023, Jul	Grandparents University, Teaching Assistant	Madison, WI
2023, Spr.	Monona Grove Liberal Arts Charter School, LEGO Fun Camp Mentor	Madison, WI
2020, Fall	4H Wisconsin, Junkdrawer Robotics Mentor	Oneida, WI
2017-Cur.	First Lego League Volunteer, Referee and Robot Design Judge	Turkey & USA
May 2019	World Robot Olympiad, Referee	Turkey
2011	LEGO Robot Education Mentor, Mentored in several STEM summer camps to teach	Turkey
	underprivileged middle school students robotics and science.	

PEER REVIEW

- ACM/SIG Conferences: CHI, HRI, DIS, IDC, HAI
- Journals: International Journal of Social Robotics, International Journal of Child Computer Interaction, Interaction Studies Journal, Frontiers in Robotics and Al

GRANTS CONTRIBUTED TO

NSF Award # 1906854, 2247381, 2202802